DAN KLEIN: Now we're going to think
about the problem of what you do in a
game like Pacman where there are
so many states that you can't
learn about each one.
The basic idea we're going to have here
is called approximate Q-Learning
and boils down to the fact that, when
you learn that a ghost is scary
through one experience, you should
transfer that to all other states that
are similar.
So we want to be able to generalize
across states because there's just so
many of them.
In basic Q-Learning, if you think about
the algorithm, it keeps a table
of all of the Q-values.
That looks something like this.
You have your agent and, for every
cell of grid world and for every
action, you have a number
that you're storing.
That's fine when there are
too many Q-states.
In any kind of realistic situation,
this won't actually work.
And the reason it won't work is because
we can't learn about every
single state.
There are multiple reasons why we can't
learn about every single state.
There are too many of them to
visit them all in training.
You just can't get yourself in every
configuration of Pacman.
In addition, even if you could, there's
too many states even hold the
Q-values in memory.
So even if you wanted to do exhaustive
Q-Learning, it's not an option.
In general, for a game like Pacman, if
you had the Q-tables, it would just be
this infinite library.
And that's not going to work.
So what we want to do is
we want to generalize.
We'd like to be able to take some small
number of training examples, our
experiences in some small number of
games, and generalize them to similar
situations.
This is actually a fundamental
idea in machine learning.
We'll see it over and over
again in this course.
You actually want to be able to
generalize not just to save on time
and storage, but also because
it's just better.
You're going to learn faster, if you
don't have to repeat the lessons in
every similar state.
For example, let's imagine that we
discover, through experience, that
this state is bad.
This is not a good state.
And in fact, we're going to
discover that very soon.
So we learn that this state is bad with
our reinforcement learning magic.
In basic Q-Learning, we know nothing at
all about this state, even though,
as a human, you look at that and think,
yeah, that's probably bad too.
In fact, it's kind of
bad in the same way.
But it's a different state.
And so you know nothing about
it in naive Q-Learning.
It's actually even worse than that.
You also know nothing
about this state.
What's wrong with this state?
It's missing a dot.
It is a totally different state, as
far as Q-Learning is concerned.
Something's wrong here, if you've got
to learn about the ghosts in every
configuration of not only
ghost, but also dot.
Let's look at what this would do.
So what happens when we run
reinforcement learning in Pacman?
So this is going to be a very
small Pacman board.
And what you're going to see is you're
going to see a bunch of states fly by.
Each state is going to have
a Q-value for each action.
And we're going to slowly
learn, so here we go.
Tiny little board.
We died.
Oh, we won.
You mostly die.
Why?
Because you don't know
what's going on.
You're like, I've never
seen this state.
Let's go left.
And meanwhile, the ghost is like yum.
[LAUGHTER]
DAN KLEIN: Every now and then you
accidentally eat the dot.
You lose a lot at Pacman this way.
The regret is very high.
Now what I'm going to do is I'm going
to let it run 2,000 times before we
see anything.
After 2,000 times, you've seen
all these states before.
You know exactly which
ones are good or bad.
And now you can do some amazing
gymnastics and dodge the ghost.
And in fact, that was a win.
So you win, and you win, and
you win, and you win.
So that's great.
Q-Learning on Pacman.
Or does it?
What about this?
This board isn't much bigger, but it
just takes a long time before you find
your way to that dot.
And the ghost just isn't
going to let you do it.
And what are you learning?
You're like, oh, in square 2,
comma 3, it's kind of bad to
run into the ghost.
Oh, in square 1, comma 2, maybe I
shouldn't run into the ghost.
[LAUGHTER]
DAN KLEIN: Yeah.
So that's basically not going to work.
So what's the solution?
You actually already know the solution,
because you already
implement it in project two.
The solution is to take a state and,
rather than thinking about it as its
own black box whose Q-values values
are special and unlike any other
state's Q-values, instead, what we say
is, really, states boil down to a
small number of properties, which
we will call features.
So we describe a state using a vector
of features, just like we did for
evaluation functions.
So what are features?
They take a state and they
return a real number.
Sometimes it's 0/1, indicating
something.
And sometimes it's a number indicating
something that's a real number.
And so, for example, we might have the
distance to the closest ghost, or the
reciprocal of the distance to the
closest ghost, or the number of
ghosts, or 1 over the squared
distance to a dot.
Is Pacman in a tunnel?
That might be a 0/1 thing.
So you could learn that being
in a tunnel is dangerous.
You could conceivably have a feature
which says, is it the exact state
that's shown on this slide?
Of course, if you did that, you
wouldn't have 10 features.
You'd have 10 billion features.
And then it would be a lot harder to
learn, even though you're using a
feature-based representation.
In your project twos, the
thing you described with
features was a state value.
So you described a state.
You computed a value for that state by
taking your features and doing some
weighted linear combination.
Of course, now we're going to have to
describe Q-states, which gives us
features like, am I moving towards
the ghost with this action?
This gives you linear value functions.
In project two, this was your
linear value function.
It said, the value of a state is some
weighted combination of the features.
And at the time we said, you
come up with the features.
And once you have the features, you
should fiddle around with the weights
until it basically works.
Now, you're going to still come up with
the features, but the learning
algorithm is going to fiddle around
with the weights for you.
For reinforcement learning, we
have Q-values and not values.
And so what we have is Q-values that
are weighted linear combinations of
functions over state action pairs.
The advantage of having a linear
representation of your feature
function is that your experience is
now summed up with a few powerful
numbers, like ghosts are bad.
The disadvantage is you can have states
which are very similar in terms
of their features, but are
very different in value.
For example, if there are two ghosts
close to you, it matters a lot whether
they're on either side of you or both on
the same side, because in one case
you're pinned and you're a goner.
And in the other case, you
can kite them around.
Your job is to come up with features
that make sure that important
differences in value are reflected in
differences in features, so the
learning algorithm can do its job.
So how does approximate
Q-Learning work?
Well, here's the magic equation.
This equation tells us, on the basis of
the features of a state action pair
and some weights which are, for the
moment, known and fixed so we're going
to update them, it lets us
compute the Q-value.
So I give you a state.
You compute this function.
And out pops the Q-value.
How are we going to do Q-Learning
with these Q-functions?
Well, the first part of the Q-Learning
algorithm doesn't actually care where
the Q-value came from.
It says, give me a transition
so that I can learn.
And you say, all right.
I was in state, s.
I chose action, a.
And I received reward, r.
And I landed in outcome s prime.
OK.
Well, I take a difference.
I say all right, I thought I
was going to get Q of s, a.
That was my old guess on one hand.
And on the other hand, I now think I'm
going to get this reward plus my
estimate of the value of the
landing state, which is a
max over its actions.
So you compute this kind of error term,
the difference between what you
thought you were going to get and what
you actually seem to be about to get,
on the basis of this one
step ahead experience.
Now what's the update?
For an exact Q-Learner, the
update looks like this.
This is just an algebraic rewrite of
the update that says, take alpha of
one and 1 minus alpha of the other.
So what we basically do is we keep our
Q-value around, but we nudge it in the
direction of this difference, the
difference between what we thought we
would get and what we appear
to be getting.
So if we appear to be getting something
a lot higher than we
thought, well, we should
raise our estimate.
Now if your Q-values are a big table,
you simply look up this entry, s, a.
You see it's 9.3.
You cross out the 9.3, and
you replace it with 9.8.
It's really easy to increment a table.
The problem is now the only knobs
we have are the weights.
You can't increment a single
value in the Q-function.
But what you can do is you can say,
all right, my Q-value wasn't high
enough for this state, so what I need to
do is change the weights so that it
will be higher.
And the way we do that is, instead of
increasing the Q-value directly, we
increase the weights.
But which weights should we increase?
You increase all of them, but in
proportion to the feature value.
So if a certain feature is off,
we don't change its weight.
If it's negative, we're actually going
to decrease its weight, because of the
sign change.
And then, features that fire
more strongly have a bigger
effect on the update.
So this is the difference.
It's the same idea.
You compute how wrong you were.
And then you try to make
that error less.
Except now, we are tweaking
the weights, rather than
the Q-values directly.
That looks like this.
That looks like you've got these
sliders, like how bad is a ghost?
And whenever you're near a
ghost and something bad
happens, blame the ghost.
And so you write down ghosts are a
little worse than they were before.
The intuitive interpretation is we're
adjusting these weights so that, if
something bad happens, all of the
features that are active get a
penalty and so on.
OK, let's see an example of Q-Learning
with feature-based approximations
being applied to Pacman.
So here's a very simplistic version
of a Q-function for Pacman.
It says, in a given state, s, and for
a given action, a, I'm going to
compute how close will I be to
the dot, if I take action a.
And then I'll take the reciprocal
of that distance.
That's fDOT, the DOT feature.
So a big number means I'm basically
getting close to a dot.
There's also a GST feature which
computes the same thing for the ghost.
So as I get closer to the ghost,
f sub GST gets bigger.
And we've learned a Q-function that says
multiply the DOT feature by 4.
So basically, dots are very good.
But subtract off the GST feature.
So a state that has ghosts
nearby is very bad.
And let's see what happens, if we have
an experience with this Q-function.
Well, here's a state.
It's not the best state to be in.
And here, fDot is 0.5, because
the closest dot is two away.
And fGST might be 1.0, because
the ghosts are one away.
When we plug these features into the
Q-function with our current values of
4 and 1, we compute that our approximate
Q is plus 1 for this
Q-state, so for this state
and for the action NORTH.
What does that mean?
That means that, according to our
approximate Q-value, we think our
score for the game from this point
forward is going to be plus 1.
Well, what happens?
Well, reality happens.
You move NORTH, you die.
You receive a negative 500 reward.
And you end up in a state
where the game is over.
And therefore, the Q-values
are all 0, by definition.
So now we think hard and we say, well,
I used to think, before I had this
experience, that this state on
the left was worth plus 1.
Apparently, that isn't what
happened this time.
This time, it looks like I'm on track
for the negative 500 I received plus a
future discounted reward of
0 when the game ended.
All right, so I compare
these two things.
And I say, well, it looks like
I overestimated by 501.
So my difference here is negative 501.
And that means I should probably
lower the Q-value.
Now remember, I can't lower
the Q-value directly.
I have to lower it via the weights.
And so I do this update.
The weights mostly stay the same.
But I move them in the appropriate
direction by an amount that is
proportional to my error, the
learning rate, alpha--
that's a step size here--
and deactivation of the feature.
So the GST feature was more active here
than the DOT feature, so it's
going to receive a larger update.
When I execute these updates, I end up
with a new Q-function which has the
same functional form, uses the same
features, but has different weights.
We like dots slightly less, because
there was a dot relatively nearby at
our tragic demise.
And we really don't like ghosts now,
because they were right there when all
the bad stuff happened.
Now we'll continue acting, but
it seems reasonable that
this is what we learn.
We still like the dots, but now
we're more scared of ghosts.
It seems like a good outcome.
Let's see what happens in practice.
What's nice about this is
you learn so quickly.
From even one experience, you can
learn that ghosts are bad.
So what you're going to see is you're
going to see a game of Pacman in a
reasonable board with ghosts.
And what you should realize is, the
first time you eat a dot, you get a
feedback that lets you learn
that maybe dots are good.
And the first time you hit a ghost, you
have an opportunity to learn that
ghosts are bad.
So instead of that kind of error and
error and error and finally, after
2,000 tries, we master a 2x2 board,
let's see what happens.
So mm, dots are good.
Ghosts are bad.
OK, dots are good.
You see it tried to run away.
And now, pretty good.
Here, it's not eating
the power pellets.
If it ate them, it would have a chance
to learn that they're good, if the
feature functions allow that
to be represented.
In this case, those features
aren't present.
What we're going to do now is we're
going to take a quick look and see why
this update makes sense.
I told you this intuitive explanation,
which was look at your error and
adjust the weight so that
the error gets smaller.
In fact, we can use that idea to
formally justify this approximate
Q-Learning update.
And the way we do that is we think
back to a more general
case of least squares.
So in general, we might want to do some
kind of linear approximation.
In particular, we have
some feature vector.
Maybe we've only got one feature,
f1 of our input x.
And we can have a prediction
function which is linear.
In this case, there's a w0, which
is an intercept term.
That will correspond to what's
called a Bias feature that's
always equal to 1.
And here we have one real feature.
And in a linear function, I always
have a prediction that's a linear
function of my input.
So the prediction here is y hat.
This can happen in multiple
dimensions as well.
The dimension gets higher,
as I have more features.
So this is a linear prediction
function.
How do we figure out what weights we
should use in this simple case where
we simply have inputs, outputs
and some data points?
No Q-Learning, no robots,
none of that.
Well, we say all right, we've
got these data points that
are shown in red.
I've got some predictor, which
is determined by the weights.
And my predictor makes mistakes, in
particular, on a given data point.
Our actual value is y, but we predict
y hat on the basis of our weights.
Now better weights will get the
y's and the y hats closer.
Formally, we could write this down.
We could say the total error in
our predictor is a sum over
all the data points.
For each data point, we look at the
difference between the prediction and
the target.
And we square it, because being negative
is bad, and being positive is
bad as well.
So that's our total error.
Remember that our predictor
has this linear form.
For us, this linear form is with
respect to the features of x.
And that's why you see these feature
functions here that you wouldn't
normally see in a linear regression.
So we have this expression
that is our total error.
And we should move the weights around
to make this error small.
This is just how you drive
linear regression.
Well, let's think about
a particular case.
Let's say we wanted to minimize
the error on one data point.
So we imagine we have one point x.
And this point x has some
features f of x.
It's got some target value y that
we'd like the linear function to
approximate.
And we've got some weights w.
So we can write out the error
on just this one point.
So what's the error?
It's the difference between the
target and the approximation.
We square it, because negative
and positive are both bad.
And we stick a 1/2 there, because we
think ahead to how the calculus is
going to work out.
But 1/2 doesn't do anything.
So what we could do, if we wanted to
make this error small, is we could
pull out our calculus.
And we could take a derivative with
respect to a certain weight, like w
sub m for the m feature vector.
And if we did that, we'd chug through
the calculus and we'd get the
expression that says the derivative
of the error is this expression.
So to make the error big, you want to
go in the direction of the feature
vectors that are contributing
to this mistake.
What you really want to do
is make the error small.
So you go in the other direction.
And really, what that means is, for a
small step size, alpha, you take your
weight and you take a step in the
direction away from the derivative of
the error with respect to the weight.
And that is exactly our online Q-update,
which corresponds to
fiddling this line up and down.
Now how does this work in Q-Learning?
Well, the weights are the weights.
The target that you're trying to
reach is your experience from a
one-step-look-ahead.
And your prediction is
your linear function.
So in fact, this approximate Q-Learning
that had an intuitive
explanation, but came out of nowhere, it
in fact corresponds to exactly the
case of online least squares.
Now we had this question of why we want
to stick to linear things, why we
want to stick to some reasonably
small amount of features.
Well, let's say you have this data.
What are you going to do with it?
Well, in general, linear
is reasonably safe.
Let's imagine that was straight.
You might want to do something richer.
Like you might want to have not only
x as a feature, but x squared.
And if you add x and x squared as
features and you took linear
combinations of x and x squared,
in fact, you would get
quadratic fits, right?
Let's imagine that's a quadratic.
And that might be better.
And so you think this is great.
With a linear combination, because I
can be non-linear in my features, I
can fit more complicated things.
Let's throw in all kinds of
crazy non-linearities.
And let's throw in all kinds of
features, as many things as we can
possibly think of.
Well, what happens?
Well, what would happen if you tried
to fit this thing with a degree 15
polynomial?
Well, guess what?
You can fit it.
Good job.
And this isn't very good because,
although it gives you the right answer
on your data points, it's totally
useless in between.
You might as well have given it
to this guy and just said
connect these up.
This idea that you might do better, if
you limit the capacity of your model
in some way, is a general idea in
reinforcement learning where you want
to generalize and you don't
want to over-fit.